Pietro Lesci

Email: pietrolesci@outlook.com Personal Page: pietrolesci.github.io Google Scholar: pietrolesci Github: github.com/pietrolesci

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/pietrolesci

Twitter-X: @pietro_lesci

PhD student in NLP at Cambridge University with a background in econometrics. 3+ years experience across research labs, consulting firms, and international institutions training custom models and developing data science solutions. Expert in developing causal methods to study the effect of training choices on models' behaviour.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PhD Student & Research Assistant @ University of Cambridge October 2021 - present | Cambridge, UK

I work with Prof Andreas Vlachos on causal methods to study the effect of training choices on models' behaviour, including memorisation, shortcut learning, and tokenisation. My work includes:

- Curating large datasets allowing for controlled experiments
- Training language models and performing causal analysis
- Developing custom trainers for active training loops

Applied Scientist Intern @ Amazon AWS AI Labs

September 2022 - January 2023 | Barcelona, ES

I worked with Lluis Marquez on efficient dialogue state tracking with language models (published at ACL 2023). My work included:

- Developing methods to scale models to long conversations
- Fine-tuning language models for dialogue tasks
- Curating datasets for model evaluation

Senior Associate, Data Science @ Bain & Company

March 2020 - October 2021 | Milan, IT

I solved complex business problems across various industries (e.g., mining, energy) using data science. My work included:

- Generating and prioritising solutions ("80/20" approach)
- Presenting solutions and their tradeoffs to clients
- Delivering solutions within the agreed-upon time
- Coordinating the work of junior consultants on the team

Research Assistant @ Bocconi University BIDSA Center

August 2019 - March 2020 | Milan, IT

I worked with Prof Dirk Hovy on the identification of online abuse. My work included developing the Wordify and MACE web-apps.

Data Science Intern @ European Central Bank

February 2018 - November 2018 | Frankfurt am Main, DE

I worked on enriching internal databases. My work included:

- Developing custom data deduplication pipelines
- Data ingestion, integration, and quality assurance
- Reporting to experts from the National Central Banks

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] P. Lesci, C. Meister, T. Hofmann, A. Vlachos, and T. Pimentel. Causal estimation of memorisation profiles. ACL 2024.
- [2] P. Lesci and A. Vlachos. Computationally efficient active learning for large and imbalanced datasets. NAACL 2024.

AWARDS & GRANTS

Best Paper Award at ACL 2024 Our paper [1] was among the 5 winners.

Translated Imminent Research Grant Our project obtained \$20k in funding.

EDUCATION

MSc in Economic and Social Sciences @ Bocconi University

September 2016 - March 2019 | Milan, IT

Bayesian Statistics and Econometrics. Dissertation: "Deep Learning: A Statistical Perspective". Grade: 104/110

BSc in Economics and Management @ Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore

September 2013 - September 2016 | Milan, IT Macroeconomics and Agent-Based Models. Dissertation: "Market Sentiment and Monetary Policy". Grade: 110/110 cum laude

Scientific High School Diploma

September 2008 - July 2013 | Castrovillari, IT Grade: 95/100

ACADEMIC ROLES

Teaching Assistant and Thesis Supervisor

A.Y. 2022, 2023, 2024 | Cambridge, UK

Lead practical and marking sessions (course "Machine Learning and Real-world Data", 300 students). Co-supervised MSc thesis projects.

Conference Reviewer

2019 - present

Reviewed for top-ranked international conferences (ACL, EMNLP, ICLR).

SKILLS

Natural & Formal Languages

Italian (native), English (fluent), and French (basic). Python, R, Stata, SQL, LATEX, Julia, MATLAB, and Rust.

EXTRACURRICULAR

Music Education

Classical piano and jazz bass guitar.